[SPEAKER_00]: I was wondering if you could say a little bit about social, compassionate, engaged acts as a path to freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, it's a... engaged... engaged buddhism is a very big thing nowadays.
[SPEAKER_00]: And... that as a path to freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like path to arahantship?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean,
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess, depending how you define engaged, to what extent...
[SPEAKER_01]: Depending how you define engaged, but if what you... what you said, social engaged, means like engaged with society, with social work and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, the maximum amount of engagement is what the Buddha prescribed for the monks.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, first, for lay people engaging socially, compassionately... Well, that's fine, but they cannot expect the results of arahantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as a monk, devoting your time... Well, it's a contradiction in terms that you'd be better off as a layperson devoting your time to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as a monk, wearing the robe, keeping the vinaya, it's like your statement that you're practicing towards Dharmanjī, supposedly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you dress as a monk...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you are a monk, you keep the vinaya, but you act like a layperson and socially engaged.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's nice in lay terms and secular terms, and it's very worldly, but it has nothing to do with the practice of dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the Buddha was criticizing the monks who were
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite attained at the time, like Ānanda and other Theras, when they were sewing the robes, in that sutta, and they were just talking around, like, you know, they had kathina and sewing the robes, and the Buddha came and was like, what was going on here?
[SPEAKER_01]: When they said, oh, it's just Lord, you know, it's the kathina, we're sewing the robes, like, well, I thought it was like a band of fishermen, like shouting, like when they sell fish, it is this ridiculous noise, and then he rebuked them all, and Ānanda especially.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should not be socializing in that manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that was like monks with monks.
[SPEAKER_01]: For the, you know, the great purpose of the kathina, which is usually regarded as this great gathering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the Buddha just completely cut them down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they were, they were just, eh... yeah, socializing for no, eh... no dhamma purpose, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see how, how, how much more that would be the truth in case of, like, eh... socializing for something completely secular.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's nice... charity is nice, but it's no more than a good deed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if a person is practicing for Arahantship, he cannot afford, basically, to spend his time doing charity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless he can do charity completely in an undistracting manner or something, but that's highly unlikely.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the best a person can really do is free themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you contribute to the well-being of the entire humanity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being, one five aggregates less, that is trapped by saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no greater contribution towards the big perspective of saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be building hospitals and schools and everything else, and that will last, you know, maybe for hundreds of years, but that's about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if a person frees themselves, they've contributed to a basically one entire being that's been tied for eons and eons and eons,
[SPEAKER_01]: They would be freed from saṃsāra never to return.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no greater contribution towards the world than that freedom of one by one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every person can help one being make one being be themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, well, that's secondary, whether that being is yourself or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yes, it will have to be yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot do enlightenment for somebody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, when it comes to enlightenment, it ceases to be even yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remove the ownership, which is why you become enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: But from the ultimate point of view of the, like, saṃsāra and being strapped in it, that is the greatest contribution.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, person who cannot... people who cannot see beyond their sense of self and self-centeredness, they'll think, oh, well, that's just selfish, they're just doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But everything you do, everything you have a desire to do,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's selfish, because you're just fulfilling your desire, even if it's to help the others.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's not optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just want to basically see how limited your goals will be, or how expanded.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dedicating your life to something that will make a difference in the world is very limited, from the ultimate point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's certainly better than not doing anything at all, neither practicing for enlightenment, nor being generous and doing charity.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is when people start doing charity, thinking that's what leads to enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's... that's not true.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you can do a charity that won't impede your way towards enlightenment, that's absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said, it's highly unlikely you'll be able to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you might have to limit your activities towards charity and helping others, because that should not be the priority of somebody who supposedly dedicated their life towards the practice of arhantship, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: a Buddhist monk.